Finding Aid for Michigan Commission of the United Ministries in Higher Education Records, 1963-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Commission of the United Ministries in Higher Education Records 1963-1982
Michigan Commission of the United Ministries in Higher Education.
0320 Ba 2
Organization established to facilitate ecumenical and state-wide cooperation among various college and university Christian church groups. Records include historical background information; records documenting relations among the participating denominations; affiliate records; and administrative records.
9.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by The Rev. Canon William S. Logan (donor. no. 9010 ), and came to the library in 2000.
The record group is open to research.
Around 1962, the University of Michigan Episcopal and United Presbyterian campus ministries began thinking about ways in which they might work together toward common goals. Plans and proposals were set forth over the following two years. The resulting organization, formally constituted in 1964, was named the Association for Ecumenical Ministries (AEM). In 1967, AEM reorganized itself as the Association for Ministries in Higher Education (AMHE), when additional denominations - notably the United Church of Christ - joined up. In January 1969, AMHE and the Committee for United Budget and Personnel Assignment (CUBPA) proposed to unite to form what would become the MC/UMHE. In 1970 the reorganization went into effect.
Part of the impetus for change came from the denominations' determination to allow for more joint strategizing and operating. Also in 1970, the United Methodists entered the coalition; the Lutheran and American Baptist churches around this same period decided to work on their own and thus left the organization.
The MC/UMHE organization reflected the relationship that then existed among main-line denominations as well as the changing structures of these denominations. In general, each denomination was split into large statewide or regional bodies called judicatories. For instance, the Episcopalians had three judicatories that dealt with the MC/UMHE: the Michigan, Northern Michigan and Western Michigan Dioceses. The Methodists had the Detroit and Western Michigan Conferences; the Presbyterians first had the Synod of Michigan with its five Presbyteries, and later the Synod of the Covenant (which also included Ohio and Kentucky). Participation within the UMHE could be on various levels. At one level a denomination could put its entire campus ministry budget in the common pot. At the lowest level, a denomination could merely participate in planning and strategizing. Indeed, many chaplaincies and other ministries existed prior to the UMHE; they had historic roots and well-developed support networks within their denominational umbrellas. Moreover, some were already under multi-faith sponsorship.
The role of the MC/UMHE was determined to be not the central chaplaincy of which the local ministers were employees, but the facilitator, standards-bearer and advocate of the churches' needs and opportunities. Essentially, the MC/UMHE was to be the setter of policies and priorities. So, for most of its life, it had minimal staff: an Executive Director, and at times an Associate Director, with occasional financial support for a bookkeeper and/or a development officer.
Within the UMHE umbrella were local offices at the various campuses in the state. The United Ministries in Higher Education (UMHE) at Michigan State University was an ecumenical campus ministry made up of a number of Christian denominations, including the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), the United Presbyterian church, the United Methodist Church and the United Church of Christ. In January 1970, the boards of the Wesley Foundation at MSU (a United Methodist organization with an ecumenical focus) and the United Christian Campus Fellowship (UCCF)/United Ministries in Higher Education (UMHE) united to form UMHE MSU. They shared a building owned by the Wesley Foundation, paid jointly for building staffing and had periodic joint board meetings between UMHE MSU and the Wesley Foundation. This continued until 1990, when UMHE MSU and the Wesley Foundation at MSU decided to separate.
In addition to traditional religious activities such as church services, religious retreats and bible studies, UMHE was involved in many other aspects of campus life. According to their mission statement, "Since all truth has its ground in God, Christian believers in higher education are called to join with one another and with non-believers alike in the search for truth wherever it can be found." (Mission Statement, UMHE MSU Board of Directors, 1970-1989, Administrative Information). The UMHE MSU had a very strong programming focus with considerable outreach to the campus. In addition to more traditional campus ministry activities, the chapter sponsored and co-sponsored a wide range of activities and programs on social and political issues such as apartheid in South Africa and the need for world peace. UMHE MSU also sponsored a concert series called "Local Focus." These activities furthered the organization's goal of being inclusive rather than exclusive and of reaching out to a broader campus community.
During the first several years of the UMHE (as well as during the earlier AEM/AMHE period), higher education was expanding in the country as a whole. Colleges were becoming universities, teachers colleges were becoming full-fledged colleges, and new colleges and universities were being founded. The UMHE benefited during this time of growth, but as the boom ended, denominationalism arose. Individual judicatories wished to reserve their donations for their own campus ministries. As UMHE lost judicatory funding, its own importance and effectiveness declined. Even though denominations were encouraged to remain within the coalition without financial contributions, few did so. In 1979, the Presbyterian Synods left UMHE. Over the next several years the Christian Church (Disciples) and the United Church of Christ also withdrew, eventually leaving just the United Methodists and the Episcopalians. Finally, in the late 1990's, the two remaining denominations decided to disband the Commission, and in 2000 were completing the dissolution of the MC/UMHE.
The records of the MC/UMHE consist mostly of material relating to its funding and budgeting cycles, its programs and projects, and its position within the context of campus ministries from the early 1960's through the early 1980's. As such, while the record group contains mostly material created by the UMHE (or its affiliates), it also contains material created by local judicatories (and other funders) and by organizations that enjoyed the benefits of UMHE grants. The record group paints a picture of the intersection of two major segments of Michigan (and American) life during its twenty-year span: Religion and Higher Education. It also provides insight into how religious groups hoped to engage with students on the pressing issues of the times: women's rights, interracial tensions, and various international conflicts, ranging from Vietnam to El Salvador. The record group has been divided into five series: Informational/Background; Founding Organizations' Materials; Relations with Denominations; Affiliate Records; and Organizational Records.
Subjects:
Michigan Commission of the United Ministries in Higher Education.; Education, Higher--Michigan--Religious aspects.; Interdenominational cooperation--Michigan.; Universities and colleges--Michigan--Religion.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Commission of the United Ministries in Higher Education.; Religious groups--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Informational/Background
  Informational/Background is a small series consisting of the Rev. Canon William S. Logan's summary history of the organization written in 2000 on the occasion of the records being transferred to the Bentley Historical Library.
  - Historical summary prepared by Rev. Canon William S. Logan (Box 1)
- Founding Organizations' Material 1963-1979
  The Founding Organizations' Material series (1963-1979,.9 linear feet) consists mostly of the records of AEM, AMHE, and CUBPA. It includes minutes, projects, proposals, brochures, newsletters, and reports of these organizations, as well as the material documenting the formation of the MC/UMHE. The series also includes files from groups these three organizations worked with. These materials illustrate the place of the UMHE among, and its relations with, other groups supporting religious expression on college and university campuses. Prominent names likely to be encountered in these files include Lester L. Dobyns-staff of the Episcopal Diocese, chaplain at the University of Michigan, and executive for AEM, AMHE, and MC/UMHE; Judith Hill-an office manager for AMHE; William S. Logan-staff of the Diocese of Michigan, first and later the last President of MC/UMHE; David M. Price-Assistant director of the Commission; and Duane N. Vore - executive of the United Church of Christ and founder of AMHE.
  - Association for Ecumenical Ministries-General 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - AEM-Minutes 1963-1967 (Box 1)
  - AEM (Later AMHE)-Projects and Proposals 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Association for Ministries in Higher Education-General 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - AMHE-Minutes 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - AMHE-Newsletter 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - AMHE-Personnel 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - American Association for Higher Education-Newsletter 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - Campus Ministry Women--General 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - CMW-Newsletter 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Community Colleges Project (AEM, later AMHE) 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Committee for United Budget and Personnel Assignment-General 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - CUBPA-Minutes 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - CUBPA & AMHE-Joint MC/UMHE-General 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - CUBPA & AMHE-Joint MC/UMHE-Financial 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Ministry Project 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - News Notes (Newsletter of the Dept. of Higher Education, National Council of the Churches of Christ in the USA) 1966-1979 (Box 1)
  - Religion and Public Education Project 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Rich Fools' Foundation 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Science and Human Values 1973 (Box 1)
  - United Christian Campus Fellowship (National) 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement 1967 (Box 1)
  - Urban Community Resources-General 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - UCR--Minutes 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - UCR-Projects, Proposals, Reports 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Relations with Denominations 1964-1982
  The Relations with Denominations series (1964-1982, 1.5 linear feet) consists mostly of records documenting the Commission's process of getting funding from the local judicatories of its denominations. During the period of high activity of the MC/UMHE, many of the denominations carried out internal reorganizations, the results of which can be seen in the files of this series. Each denomination's budget allocation process, and the organizational structure that served campus ministries, is displayed. Thus, changes in the shape, structure, and titles of the committees/commissions that dealt with policies and funding for campus ministries can be seen through the budget applications that UMHE submitted to these varying bodies. For instance, among the Methodists, in 1976 what had been the relatively independent Area Commission on Higher Education became subsumed under the Board of Connectional Outreach as the Division of Higher Education. This decreased both its funds and the authority by which it allocated those funds. Similarly, the Presbyterians had a few reorganizations during the inclusive dates of this collection. In 1968, the divisions within Presbyteries switched from being organized along programmatic lines to being organized along functional lines. Then, over 1972-1973, the single-state synods were combined to form a few, multi-state regional synods. (Specifically, the Synod of Michigan joined with Ohio and Kentucky Synods to become the Synod of the Covenant.) These changes ultimately resulted in Michigan Presbyteries losing much of their autonomy, as budgeting and programming decisions were made from a centralized headquarters in Columbus, Ohio. Moreover, the correspondence, memos, minutes, and other materials of the series illustrate not only UMHE's relation to other programs funded by the judicatories, but also the changes in attitudes and expectations that denomination staff had towards the Commission. The series as a whole thus documents both the expansion of UMHE as it broadened its reach to new projects, ministries, and campus affiliates and its decline, as judicatories faced increasing factionalism and shrinking budgets of their own. In addition to the important names from the first series, many of which show up here as well, other names of note include: UMHE staff- David Church-from the United Methodists, delegate who served on committees and later as President of UMHE; Russell M. Fuller, and Marjorie A. Ives, office manager and executive (she filled out most of the funding applications). Staff of the denominations include: from the Christian Church (Disciples)-Eric White and James Fraley; from the Episcopalians-Thomas Atkinson and W. Gerald Lonergan; from the United Church of Christ-John Washington and John M. Rogers; from the United Methodists-Keith T. Avery and Ray Burgess; and from the United Presbyterians - George Morgan and William Brown.
  - Episcopal
    - Report on the Ministry of the Church in and with Contemporary Higher Education 1967 (Box 1)
    - Special Ministries Committee 1971-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Venture in Mission 1978 (Box 1)
    - Diocese of Michigan 1970-1977 (Box 1)
    - Diocese of Northern Michigan 1971-1978, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Lutheran
    - American Lutheran Church 1972-1975 (Box 2)
    - Lutheran Church of America 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - United Church of Christ
    - General 1964-1981 (Box 2)
    - Division of Church in Mission 1972-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - United Methodist
    - Area Commission 1970-1976, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Division of Higher Education 1974-1979, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Board of Connectional Outreach 1976-1978 (Box 2)
    - Campus Ministers Caucus 1966-1974 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Conference 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - Western Michigan Conference 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - National Relations 1968-1978 (Box 2)
  - United Presbyterian
    - General 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Synod of Michigan 1963-1972, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Synod Ministries 1970-1982 (Box 2)
    - General Correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - Major Mission Funding 1975-1978 (Box 2)
    - The Communique (Newsletter) 1974-1980, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Program Binder 1975 (Box 3)
    - Presbytery of Detroit 1966-1978 (Box 3)
    - Presbytery of Lake Huron 1969-1972 (Box 3)
    - Presbytery of Lake Michigan 1975 (Box 3)
    - Mackinac Presbytery 1968-1972 (Box 3)
  - Other
    - American Baptist 1971-1977 (Box 3)
    - Christian Church/Disciples of Christ 1964-1979 (Box 3)
    - Christian Reformed Church 1964 (Box 3)
    - Roman Catholic Church 1965 (Box 3)
- Affiliate Records
  The Affiliate Records series consists of local materials transferred to the MCUMHE office. The bulk of these records are from the Grand Valley Affiliate and the Michigan State University Affiliate.
  - Grand Valley Affiliate (Grand Valley Ministries) 1967-1982
    The records of the Grand Valley Affiliate (1967-1982, 0.6 linear feet) are from the Grand Valley Ministry at Grand Valley State College in Allendale, Michigan. They document the changes in the institution from its 'pre-history' as the Grand Valley Church, through its days as a 'House Church', to its dissolution due to lack of funding. The subseries consists of GVM's meetings, reports, announcements, corporate documents, and budget and financial documents, as well as the "museletters" sent out by GVM head Erv Bode. Other materials of note include the documents surrounding the Self-Study commissioned by the UMHE, the Self-Study itself, and miscellaneous items illustrating the Ministry's interests, projects, and programs in and around the area. Taken together, the series demonstrates the relation of UMHE to its local ministries on a general level. Specifically, it shows the Ministry's everyday functioning, the connections between GWM and GVSC, and the relations of an individual ecumenical ministry with the various denominations that supported it (in this case the United Church of Christ, the United Methodists, the United Presbyterians, and the Christian Church (Disciples)).
    - Grand Valley Church (Pre-GVM) 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - General 1969-1982 (Box 3)
    - Minutes 1969-1982 (Box 3)
    - "Museletters" and announcements 1969-1975 (Box 3)
    - Financial 1969-1981 (Box 3)
    - Corporate Documents 1971-1981 (Box 3)
    - Personnel 1967-1981 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising Committee 1970-1981 (Box 3)
    - Campus Ministry Council 1971-1975 (Box 3)
    - College IV 1974 (Box 3)
    - Religious Studies Institute-History 1967-1974 (Box 3)
    - Relations with UMHE 1970-1981 (Box 3)
    - UMHE Budget & Review 1970-1980 (Box 3)
    - UMHE Self-Study-About 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - UMHE Self-Study-Submitted Document 1974 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Programs, Interests, and Activities 1969-1982 (Box 3)
  - Saginaw Valley State University
    - Campus Religious Program 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - Ypsilanti Affiliate
    - Record book 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - 1983 report (Box 3)
  - Michigan State University Affiliate
    The Michigan State University Affiliate subseries contains records of the board of directors and general administrative and historical information including record books of the executive committee, program files, and publicity. The programs sponsored by the MSU affiliate were many and diverse and involved the various aspects of campus life and the general social concerns of society. Included were such current issues as apartheid in South Africa, Women's Issues, AIDS, and global Peace.
    - Administrative information (Box 4)
    - General Information (Box 4)
    - Executive Committee record books 1970-1989, 3 volumes; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - UMCE Commission (Box 5)
    - Committee Files
      - Finance Committee 1979-1981 (Box 5)
      - Personnel Committee 1977-1990 (Box 5)
      - Program Committee 1974-1990 (Box 5)
    - Finance
      - Budgets 1975-1991 (Box 5)
      - Financial Statements 1978-1990 (Box 5)
      - Grants (Box 5)
    - Personnel
      - General Information (Box 5)
      - Internships and Sabbaticals (Box 5)
      - Job Descriptions (Box 5)
      - Lacy, Jon 1978-1990 (Box 5)
      - Volunteer Information (Box 5)
    - Programs and Publicity
      - Africa (Box 5)
      - Cults (Box 5)
      - Health/Wellness (Box 5)
      - Local Focus (Concert Series) (Box 5)
      - Ministry (Box 5)
      - Newsletters
        - Almond Branch 1969-1985 (Box 5)
        - New Wine 1971-1972 (Box 5)
      - Outreach/Recruitments (brochures, handouts, flyers) (Box 5)
      - Peacemaking (Box 5)
      - Photographs and Slides (Box 5)
      - Sexuality (Box 5)
      - Surveys (Box 5)
      - Women's Issues (Box 5)
- Organizational Records
  The Organizational Records series includes annual and quarterly reports, minutes of the executive committee, various grant proposals and applications, and photographs.
  - Annual reports (Box 5)
  - Quarterly reports (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee minutes 1977-1980s (Box 6)
  - Self-study and review 1975 (Box 6)
  - Danforth Study 1964 (Box 6)
  - "Select" Judicatory Committee (Box 6)
  - Judicatory Boards (Box 6)
  - Newsletter: The Network Reporter (Box 6)
  - Grant proposals and applications 1982-1987 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous unprocessed (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous unprocessed (Box 9)
    (continued)
  - Photographs and slide presentations (Box 10)